原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/z49eVQ6LxIE
原视频发布日期：20181116
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
这期视频主要是讲2010年以前SLS的原型变迁
而重点讲2010年以后商业载人计划的是
b23.tv/av883445957
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
In July 2011 Space Shuttle Atlantis launched on STS 135, the last Space Shuttle mission
2011年7月 亚特兰蒂斯号航天飞机进行了最后一次航天飞机任务(STS-135)的发射
and since then the US has not had the ability to launch crew into space.
而从那时起 美国就没有能力进行轨道级载人航天发射了
Since then of course all crew have traveled to the space station using the Russian Soyuz launch vehicle,
当然从那时起 所有的乘员都是使用俄罗斯的联盟号运载火箭前往国际空间站的
a design which actually dates from the 1960s.
而联盟号的设计 其实可以追溯到上世纪60年代
实际上鸽子了一年，2020年5月30日才发射了载人的载人龙飞船验证2(Crew Dragon Demo 2)任务
But next year will see the return of domestic launch capability
但明年 美国将重获载人发射能力
in the form of SpaceX's Dragon and Boeing's Starliner.
这种能力将以SpaceX的龙飞船和波音的星际客机的形式体现
And I can sense there's a number of you out there
我可以感觉到你们中的一些人
already grumbling about this terrible gap in US launch capabilities,
已经在抱怨美国载人发射能力的这种可怕缺口
asking why wasn't there a replacement for this Space Shuttle.
会问为什么航天飞机退役时没有相应的替代品出现
Well the truth is there have been many replacements for the Space Shuttle developed
那么事实是 有很多替代航天飞机的产品已经研发出来了
but none of them actually ended up flying.
但最终都没有真正飞起来
Well at least not yet. We can look forward to the SLS,
好吧 至少还有一个快飞了 我们还可以期待一下SLS
a launch vehicle derived from Space Shuttle components,
这是由航天飞机部件衍生出来的运载火箭
the Boosters, the engines, the tank.
这包括助推器 发动机 储罐
It seems like such a logical idea you'll wonder why nobody has tried it before.
这似乎是一个合理的想法 你会奇怪为什么以前没有人尝试过
Except, this picture here isn't the SLS.
只是 这张照片不是SLS
This is the NLS, the National Launch System.
这是NLS 国家发射系统
This was investigated back in 1991
这在1991年就被研究过了
and if you put it right next to the SLS, you can see there's a lot in common.
如果你把它放在SLS旁边 你可以看到有很多共同点
A pair of Space Shuttle boosters
一对航天飞机助推器
helping to lift an orange cryogenic propellant tank and a cluster of main engines.
用于推进一个橙色的低温推进剂储罐 (而在这储罐下面是)一堆主发动机
Except that this isn't an SLS.
不过这不是SLS
This is Ares 5 from the constellation program.
这是星座计划中的战神5号火箭
But this ladies and gentlemen is the real deal.
但这个 女士们先生们 这个是真的那个SLS
Or at least an artist's impression of the real deal because the real deal is still being built.
或者说至少是真货的艺术效果图 因为真货还在建造中
these are what are called Shuttle-derived vehicles because of course they're derived from Shuttle components
这些是所谓的航天飞机的衍生运载火箭 这是因为它们都是从航天飞机的部件中衍生出来的
and these are have been a very easy sell to politicians
并且很容易让政客们接受
because of course you know first of all you can say that
因为 首先你可以这么假设
since you're reusing Shuttle components, it means that you don't have to do all that expensive R&D
既然你在重复使用航天飞机的部件 这意味着你不必重复那些昂贵的研发工作了
but more importantly it means you get to keep the same contractors happy.
但更重要的是 这意味着你可以让同样一群承包商们满意
And of course that was incredibly important for any politician which was looking at replacing the Space Shuttle
当然 对于那些正考虑替换航天飞机的政治家来说 (让老商人们满意)是非常重要的
because you did not want to be the person getting blamed for thousands of people potentially losing their jobs
因为你不想被成千上万的失业的人们所指责
after their the essential space gizmo got eliminated from that all-important contract.
而这些人正是因为关键性的合同被取消 导致相关航天产品被砍掉才失业的
As it happens,
恰好
the suppliers didn't even wait until the Space Shuttle was launched before coming up with their alternative ideas.
供应商甚至在航天飞机发射前就提出他们的替代想法
This concept art from Thiokol.
这张来自Thiokol的概念图
Again looks very similar to what we're talking about today,
同样和我们今天要谈的东西非常相似
in terms of the SLS with a pair of strap-on boosters and a core tank.
与SLS的外形相比 它也是一对捆绑助推器和一个芯级(液体火箭)储罐
Of course because this was before the Space Shuttle really started flying
当然因为这是在航天飞机真正开始飞行之前的事情
the external tank was still white back then.
那时候的外储罐还是白色的
Also around this time Boeing seriously looked at
也是在这个时候 波音认真研究了一下
replacing the orbiter with its wings and crew cabin with a much more basic payload fairing with engines attached.
用一个更基本的有效载荷整流罩替代了轨道器的机翼和乘员舱 并安装了发动机
They came up with potential payloads of up to 68 tons
这个方案的有效载荷能力可能高达68吨
关于Shuttle C等计划的解读，详见youtu.be/Qi7wtXcaFws
and by the mid 80s, this actually became seriously considered in the form of Shuttle C.
到了80年代中期 这个方案被称为C式太空梭 并被认真考虑过
Now this had serious research time and money put into it
那么 这个方案确实花费了大量的研制时间和金钱
as evidenced by the fact that instead of concept art we have these high quality 1980s computer graphics.
因为我们看到的不是概念图 而是这些高质量 的80年代计算机图形
Anyway the designers went through many iterations of the design
总之 设计师们经过了多次的设计迭代
but you know they typically were looking at launching 45 to 50 tons per launch
但在这个方案里 他们通常会考虑每次发射45到50吨的货物
and this was of course pitched as being a great way
当然 这也被宣传是一个很好的方式
to support the forthcoming Space Station Freedom concept.
来支持即将推出的自由空间站概念
One problem was that the Space Shuttle main engines were pretty expensive
其中一个问题是 航天飞机的主发动机相当昂贵
about thirty eight million dollars each.
每台约为三千八百万美元
So the designers proposed that they would only use engines that had already flown on Shuttles
所以设计者提出 他们只使用已经在航天飞机上飞行过的发动机
and which had essentially reached the end of their useful life.
这种发动机基本已达到其使用寿命(即使丢掉也不可惜)
This seemed nice on paper but the problem was that it then limited the number of launches
这在纸面上似乎很好 但问题是它限制了发射的次数
and if they were gonna use fresh engines then that would be a whole lot more expensive.
如果他们要使用新的发动机 那么整体将更昂贵
Ultimately it ended up looking like
最终 它看起来像是
the whole thing would have cost more per kilogram than the most expensive expendable launch vehicles at the time.
每公斤的发射成本会超过当时最昂贵的一次性运载火箭
And so in 1990 the program was officially canceled
所以在1990年 这个计划被正式取消了
but not before they had built this rather nice mock-up.
但至少他们先做了这个相当漂亮的模型
The year after I guess there was a little room in the budget
后来几年 我猜是预算有了余裕
so some money was spent to study the National Launch System.
所以花了一些钱来研究国家发射系统
Now while this never flew,
那么虽然它从来没有飞过
one interesting part of this is the engines on that.
其中一个有趣的部分是它的发动机
Those aren't Space Shuttle main engines.
这使用的就不是航天飞机的主发动机
Those are Space Transportation Main Engines.
而叫太空运输系统主发动机(STME)
RS-25E：感觉有被冒犯到
The idea being to take the Space Shuttle main engine and create a cheaper expandable version.
这个发动机的设计理念是基于航天飞机的主发动机来研制一个更便宜的一次性版本
And development and testing of hardware did actually happen along these lines at Aerojet.
而设备的开发和测试也确实是按照这样的思路在Aerojet公司进行的
Of course it never eventually appeared as the STME
当然最终这台发动机也没有以STME的形式出现
But it did become the RS-68 which powers the Delta IV.
但它确实成为了德尔塔四火箭的发动机RS-68
The National Launch System didn't get very far
国家发射系统并没有走得很远
because it entered a world where they were having to pay for the Space Station freedom
因为在它那个世界线时代 美国需要花钱造自由空间站
and the Space Shuttle program
以及维持航天飞机计划
so a third very expensive program just wasn't on the cards.
那么再来第三个非常昂贵的计划是万万不能的
The lots of white papers and studies from the era continued to use as a baseline for a launch vehicle
许多那个时代的白皮书和研究报告 继续作为(新)运载火箭的原型
for getting spacecraft that would ultimately go to the Moon or Mars.
这种火箭将最终前往月球或火星
Anyway most of the 90s remained focused on the space station and the Space Shuttle
总之 90年代的大部分时间仍然集中在空间站和航天飞机上
but 2000 brought this space launch initiative including the X-33 test vehicle.
但2000年带来了这一太空发射计划(指冒险星) 包括X-33试验飞行器
This was a sub scale test vehicle
这是小型化的试验飞行器
which would explore the technologies required for single-stage-to-orbit operation,
被用于研究单级入轨飞行所需的技术
关于气尖发动机的解读，详见b23.tv/av841875408
including your novel composite materials and the linear aerospike engine.
包括新颖的复合材料和线性气尖发动机
It was probably the most famous part of the space launch initiative
这可能是太空发射计划中最著名的部分
and unfortunately after about 80% plus of the vehicle had been built, it was cancelled.
而不幸的是 在航天器制造了80%多之后 就被取消了
In particular it's often cited
特别是这取消的结局经常被这样引述
that they had issues and delays with developing the composite fuel tanks to contain liquid hydrogen and oxygen.
开发人员在研制液氢和液氧的复合材料储罐时出现了问题和延误
Some at the time even said that the materials were incompatible with cryogenic operation
当时有人甚至说 这种材料不能用于低温时的操作(如低温加注燃料)
but time has they're proven them wrong.
但时间已经证明他们是错的
They did actually solve the various problems even after the vehicle was then no longer gonna fly.
甚至在当时的计划被取消之后 他们仍然解决了各种问题
And then of course in 2003 the Columbia disaster
当然在2003年的哥伦比亚号灾难中
brought into focus the fact that they needed to come up with a replacement for the Space Shuttle.
让人们关注到这样一个事实 那就是需要一个替代航天飞机的方案
And so in 2005 the constellation program was born.
于是在2005年 星座计划诞生了
It included a number of Ares rockets derived from the Space Shuttle hardware.
计划中包括一些由航天飞机硬件衍生出来的战神火箭
It also included the Orion capsule which does actually exist
它还包括延续至今的猎户座飞船
and has actually been built into something that has flown and will fly.
而且已经被实际制造出来 并被发射过 而且将要进行发射
Now the original Ares 5 design would be using the RS-68 engines that were designed to be expendable.
那么 战神5号最初的设计将使用一次性的RS-68发动机
However towards the end of the program,
然而在计划的最后
it was realized that having a carbon ablative nozzle next to
大家意识到 把碳烧蚀喷管安装在
these giant solid rocket boosters that were designed for the Space Shuttle
为航天飞机设计的巨大的固体火箭助推器的旁边
would lead to too much heat that would actually cause the nozzle to erode too quickly.
会导致热量过高 实际上会导致喷管过快地烧蚀(而不能使用)
And so therefore they had to upgrade it to Space Shuttle main engines
因此他们只能将其升级为(使用再生冷却而非烧蚀冷却的)航天飞机主发动机
and that then became pretty much the direct ancestor of what is the SLS.
而这也成为了SLS的直接原型
And in 2009 the constellation program did actually get a vehicle flying.
而在2009年 确实有一枚星座计划的火箭进行了发射
This is the Ares I.
这就是战神一号
It's essentially a solid rocket booster from the Space Shuttle with an upper stage bolted on
基本上就是给航天飞机的固体火箭助推器扣了一个上面级
that was supposed to carry a crewed vehicle into orbit.
这样 通过上面级将载人飞船送入轨道
This would be essentially the equivalent of the Soyuz.
这基本上相当于联盟号飞船
It would transport crew to and from the space station.
通过战神一号(和猎户座)让乘员往返于空间站
The launch was a partial success.
这次发射取得了部分成功
It did have issues with the booster recontacting the upper stage and other problems like that.
它确实出现了助推器与上面级重新接触等问题
But there was also sort of relatively notorious paper published by the US Air Force
但美国空军也发表了一篇相对臭名昭著的论文
that demonstrated that the abort system on this was hideously dangerous
证明了这上面的中止系统是非常危险的
and would pretty much result in everyone dying if they had to abort during this launch
如果在发射中使用中止系统 几乎会导致每个人都死掉
because the debris the you're coming off of this would destroy any parachutes.
因为固推爆炸产生的碎片会破坏任何降落伞
But that wouldn't kill it.
但并不是这个原因导致了项目的结束
No. What would kill it would be the fact
不 结束这个项目的其实是
that the constellation program was hideously over budget and behind schedule by 2009.
星座计划严重超支问题 而且到2009年已落后于计划
And in parallel another program had been started called commercial orbital transportation services.
而与此同时 另一项名为商业轨道运输服务的计划也已经启动
This includes the commercial cargo transportation we already see in terms of Dragon and Cygnus
这包括我们已经看到的商业货物运输项目 也就是龙飞船和天鹅座
and it was also looking at expanding the scope to include crew services.
而且还在考虑扩大范围 把载人服务也包括在内
So in 2009 there is a report called the Augustine report which pretty much published all this stuff
所以在2009年的时候 奥古斯丁报告几乎把这些星座计划的负面数据都公布出来了
and so the government decided that it was better to cancel the constellation program
所以政府决定 最好是取消星座计划
and focus on commercial services instead.
而专注于商业服务
But then a year later a slightly reduced scope version comes along.
但一年后 一个范围略微缩小的版本出现了
It keeps a Orion capsule which was pretty far into development at that point
它保留了猎户座飞船 这在当时已经是进行了相当深入的开发了
and then it essentially creates the SLS which was the Ares 5 modified.
然后 它基本上创造了战神5火箭的改进型号 也就是SLS
of course this was very popular with politicians
当然这是非常受政治家欢迎的
because again it made sure that that Shuttle money was gonna continue flowing to the various contractors
因为它再次确保了航天飞机的钱会继续流向各个承包商
that were supplying the engines and rockets and various other materials.
也就是提供发动机和火箭以及其他各种材料的那些公司
And that mostly brings us up to date.
而这些主要就是我们现在了解到的情况了
The year after the Shuttle stopped flying,
在航天飞机停飞后的那一年
SpaceX started delivering cargo to the space station
SpaceX开始向空间站运送货物
and next year we're gonna get a Dragon and Starliner flying.
而明年我们就会看到龙飞船和星际客机进行发射了
But we probably could have had Commercial Crew running a bit sooner.
但也许商业载人计划曾经有可能更早进行
It was terribly underfunded early on.
这是因为该计划早期投入的资金严重不足
Richard Shelby自2005年(109届国会)起担任参议院科学拨款小组委员会(CJS Subcommittee)主席，
支持星座计划，反对商业载人计划(带恶人)，自2018年后升任拨款委员主席，他与SLS有重大利益相关
In particular Senator Richard Shelby used his role in Appropriations committees
特别是参议员Richard Shelby利用他在拨款委员会的地位
出处www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2014-06-23/spacex-versus-senator-shelby-s-rocket-to-nowehere
to stack the deck against Commercial Crew and divert money to the SLS program.
把钱从商业载人计划转到SLS项目上
出处www.parabolicarc.com/2014/06/04/space-access-society-action-alert-shelby-wreck-commercial-crew/
And then later he had the gall to argue
然后 后来他竟厚颜无耻地摇脣鼓舌道
that because Commercial Crew was now behind schedule
因为商业载人计划现在推迟进行
出处arstechnica.com/science/2017/06/senator-complains-about-cost-increases-in-nasas-fixed-price-contracts/
that it should lose even more of its money to SLS.
所以甚至需要把更多的钱转给SLS(?)
请暂停观看
出处spaceflightnow.com/2015/06/11/commercial-crew-spaceships-face-likely-delays/
高亮部分翻译：纳尔逊(参议员)说，“据说被砍的钱，也就3亿多美元，
我们如果还向俄罗斯人支付这笔钱，让他们多飞两年，就会失去这笔钱。
我们需要清醒地认识到发生了什么。”
Of course this hasn't stopped him trying to claim credit
当然 这并没有阻止他抢功的骚操作
请暂停观看
出处www.facebook.com/RichardShelby/posts/10156520406229798/
以下为上方文字翻译：
美国航天史上激动人心的一天! NASA宣布，9名勇敢的宇航员被选中驾驶波音和SpaceX的商业载人飞船，
其中一部分将由联合发射联盟在迪凯特制造的宇宙神五火箭进行发射。
期待着这个新时代，我们再次从美国本土进行载人发射。
译者注：然后波音的星际客机就拉垮了
when the astronauts were announced for the Commercial Crew program
在宣布参加商业载人计划的宇航员名单的时候
but look to be fair a Shuttle replacement was sorely needed a long time before 2009.
但是说实话 在2009年之前研制出航天飞机的替代品确实需要很长的时间
All these programs really suffered from the problem
所有这些计划真正遭受的问题在于
that the the Shuttle may have had its issues but it was good enough
航天飞机可能有它的问题 但它(当时被认为)已经足够好了
until suddenly it wasn't going to be flying anymore.
直到突然间它不打算再飞了
To be clear SLS does have its uses.
要明确的是 SLS确实有它的用途
it does have its niches.
它确实有要完成的工作
Although some might argue that the uses are being designed around the SLS.
虽然有些人可能会说 这些用途是围绕着SLS设计的
视频制作时，商业化的载人登月系统(HLS)还未出现
But it's easy to see that there are things that basically SpaceX and ULA aren't set up to do.
但很容易看出 有些事情 基本上是SpaceX和ULA不会安排去做的
But in the near future we should see crew transportation removed from that list.
但在不久的将来 我们应该会看到(空间站)乘员运输能从这个名单中删除
To switch over to Commercial Crew transportation services, it has been slow.
商业载人运输服务的切换一直以来是缓慢的
It has been painful but ultimately it's probably the best thing.
一直以来是痛苦的 但最终它可能是最好的事情
Not just for NASA but for space industry as a whole.
不仅仅是对NASA 对整个航天行业也是如此
So I like many of you will be looking forward to these commercial launches for next year.
所以我和你们很多人一样 都会期待明年的商业发射
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]